<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A briefe collection of the church, and of certayne ceremonies thereof gathered by Thomas Sampson</title>
            <author>Sampson, Thomas, 1517?-1589.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1581</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 77 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11429</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21682</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112207</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847465</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847465</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12501</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11429)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12501)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1583:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A briefe collection of the church, and of certayne ceremonies thereof gathered by Thomas Sampson</title>
                  <author>Sampson, Thomas, 1517?-1589.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>78 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H. Middleton for George Bishop,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno 1581.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Some pages marked; some print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Customs and practices --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12501:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12501:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A BRIEFE collection of the Church, and of certayne Ceremonies thereof, gathered by <hi>Thomas Sampſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by H. Middleton, for <hi>George Biſhop.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>ANNO</hi> 1581.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:12501:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:12501:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT worſhipful Maſter Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis Haſtinges, Sheriffe of Leiceſterſhire.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the French hiſtorie, which you did leaue with mee, I did find the whole hiſtorie of the <hi>Colloquie</hi> had at <hi>Poiſsie</hi> much more largely written in French, than euer I did ſee it in Latine. At this <hi>Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quie</hi> the <hi>Cardinal</hi> of <hi>Loraine,</hi> being the chiefe, and capitaine on the part of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, made an oratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> more glorious in ſhew, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſound in trueth. The which to doe, hee had both the aduiſe, and prompting of the papiſtes aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bled vnder him; as of that ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till <hi>Sorboniſt Deſpenſe,</hi> &amp; of that little furie <hi>Xaintes,</hi> with their mates. Thus being vnderpropped, this Cardinall made an oration touching two pointes; The one was of the Church; the other of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is called the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Altar. This later point by
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:12501:3"/>
him handled after his ſort, did ſo pleaſe our Papiſtes, that ſome of them did both tranſlate, and publiſhe it in Engliſh, being as it were taken hott out of the Cardinalls mouth. The ſeconde part touching the Church he handled like a Cardinall, pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Rome</hi> ſo cunningly as he coulde; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derpropping it with the holow, and rotten postes of <hi>Viſibilitie,</hi> of <hi>perſonall ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsion,</hi> and <hi>ordinarie calling,</hi> (as they call it,) and ſuch like ſtuffe. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with did he driue with might and maine to deface the true Church of Chriſte, into which it hath pleaſed God to call vs, to whome he hath giuen grace to profeſſe his holy gospell. Our Church hee woulde de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face, becauſe wee haue not thoſe rotten pillers of <hi>viſibilitie, perſonall ſucceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and <hi>ordinarie calling,</hi> in ſuch ſorte as he claimeth them for <hi>Rome.</hi> I founde in your booke a verie ſhort, but a pithie an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere made to this latter part of the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinalls oration touching the Church; the which, becauſe I had not read it before,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:12501:3"/>
did eaſily holde me in it. I liked it well, and ſo (I thinke) will you. I haue not the skill to be a perfect tranſlator out of the French tongue; neither doe I take vppon me ſo to do; But yet I haue truely ſet downe in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh the whole matter conteined in the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere. That little, which I haue added to that which is in the French, is not from the purpoſe, I truſt. This I giue to you now, as I did before, <hi>A briefe confeſsion of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chriſtian faith,</hi> which I founde in that booke; And one thing more by the grace of God I intend to giue hereafter, if I may ſee the other volumes accordinge to your promiſe. This little ſcrappe taken out of the large French booke I ſende to you; not that you neede it, for you doe vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the French tongue much better than I; but I giue it to you, to the ende that it may remaine with you, as a teſtimonie of my dutie of thankefulneſſe to you, for your great good will alwayes borne towards me; &amp; that by theſe Engliſhed ſcraps, you may be prouoked at your leaſure to reade the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:12501:4"/>
whole booke your ſelfe; and in the meane time, you may communicate in Engliſhe, ſome part of that good, which is in the French booke, to ſuch as you thinke good. Accept my poore labour in good part, I pray you. I ſhall indeuour to doe more, God of his goodnes ayding me; to whoſe goodnes, and directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on I doe commende you.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in Chriſt <hi>T. S.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:12501:4"/>
            <head>A BRIEFE COL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of the Church, <hi>Gathered by T.S.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE name of the church is in greeke <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, whiche worde is alſo taken out of an other Greek word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which ſignifieth to call a man from one place, or ſtate of life to another. And we doe finde in the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures that there are two kinds of cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The one is ioyned with the effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacie, power, and worke of the holy ghoſt. Of which kinde of calling, the Apoſtle doth ſpeake in the Epiſtle to the Romans, where he ſaith, that <hi>God doth iuſtifie them, whom he hath called.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The other calling is of leſſe force, &amp; efficacie, becauſe men are deafe, and dul, ſuch as wil not heare, nor vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande. Of this kinde of calling doth
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:12501:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the Lorde Ieſus ſpake, ſaying, <hi>Manie are called, but few are choſen.</hi> This name <hi>Church,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matt. 20.</note> therefore, in the cauſe which we haue in hande, doth ſignifie the companie of them which are called, and gathered together by the voice of God, who doth by his owne word call them. In the which company we do ſee two ſorts of men. For, taking y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word <hi>Church</hi> generally to compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hende all them which are called, and doe make an outwarde profeſſion to obey the voyce of God, wherby they are called, doubtles among them ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hypocrites are to be founde, and reprobates; as both the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſpeaketh of the Church, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience doth declare to be true. But if you will take this worde <hi>Church</hi> more properly, and ſtraitly, as often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time it is to be taken; then wee muſt ſay, that it ſignifieth only the aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of the elect of God, and of thoſe his children, whom God hath prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:12501:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
to life euerlaſting.</p>
            <p>This church is called, and is the body of Chriſt, members of his bodie, bone of his bones, and fleſh of his fleſh. In which number the repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate cannot be conteyned; For they are the members of the diuel. It is vnpoſsible for one to be a member of Chriſt, and a member of the diuel at one time; as <hi>Augustine</hi> well no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth.<note place="margin">Lib. 2. cont. Creſc. ca. 21.</note>
            </p>
            <p>This diſtinction of the name of the church the ſame father vſeth, writing vppon the threeſcore and fourth Pſalme, when he ſayeth, that <hi>the Church, which is ſignified by Hieruſalem, had the beginning in Abel; and that which is ſignified by Babylon, did begin in Cain.</hi> And yet in his booke written of baptiſme againſt the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiſtes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. 1. ca. 16.</note> taking this word <hi>Church</hi> in the more general ſignificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that it is it, which engendred <hi>Abel, Enoch, Noah, Abraham,</hi> &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:12501:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
&amp; alſo that it engendred <hi>Cain, Iſmael, Dathan,</hi> and ſuch other like to them. To conclude this matter, let vs take that which <hi>Auguſtine</hi> writeth in that ſame treatiſe;<note place="margin">Lib. 7. ca. 19.</note> &amp; that other place which is taken out of <hi>Hierome,</hi> and is cited in the decrees 24. <hi>Q.</hi> 1. <hi>Omnibus conſideratis;</hi> where it is ſaid, that there are two ſortes, or manners of men in the Church: One ſort are the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſt, and the verie true Church; and are in ſuch ſort of the houſe of God, that they are the houſe of god it ſelfe: whereby it may be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered that the other ſort are in the houſe of God, but are not of it at all; They are as chaffe mingled with the Wheate, vntill they be fanned out of it. Hereof nowe will ariſe this queſtion;<note place="margin">Viſibilitie of the Church.</note> that is, whether the church be viſible, or not. Truely God alone doth know the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which are his electe; and we do profeſſe that <hi>we doe beleeue the holy Church.</hi> But a man is not
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:12501:6"/>
ſaide properly to beleeue that, which hee ſeeth. For beleefe is of thinges not ſeene, but of ſuch thinges as God hath promiſed, though they bee not ſeene with the bodilie eye. Nowe of viſibilitie I ſay, that as Chriſt Ieſus our Lorde, beeing in the worlde to worke the worke of our ſaluation, was viſible in the glorie, and maieſtie of the true <hi>Meſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah;</hi> ſo is his true Church viſible in the worlde.<note place="margin">Iohn. 17.</note> For as hee was in the world, ſo are they which are his; that is, his true Church, in the worlde; ſo ſeene, and viſible, that the children of God, the verie elect of God, are both illuminate to ſee it, &amp; to ioyn them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to it; as <hi>Simeon, Anna, Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charie,</hi> and other, did ſee, and ioyne themſelues to the perſon of <hi>Meſsiah.</hi> So did that blinde man, which was cured, as we doe reade in the goſpell.<note place="margin">Iohn. 9.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 4.</note> Likewiſe did y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſimple woman who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt Ieſus did vouchſafe to teach
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:12501:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
in the ſame Goſpell, ſee more of the glorie, and maieſtie of the true <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah</hi> in the perſon of Ieſus, than did al the biſhops, prieſts, Scribes, and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees, which caryed the countenance, and credit of the Church among me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And as <hi>Obadiah</hi> did ſee,<note place="margin">1. Reg. 18.</note> and ioyne himſelfe to the true Church of God, in the darke dayes of <hi>Achab:</hi> It is alſo ſo viſible, that ſatan is ſuffred to eſpie it, and by his members to perſecute it; euen as hee did the perſon of our Lorde Ieſus, who is the heade of his true Church. If men wil not content themſelues with this ſight, but will haue their ſight ſatiſfied after their fanſie, with a viſible, &amp; worldly glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of a church in this worlde, more viſible than Chriſt himſelfe was, whoſe Church in this worlde ſhall haue, and bee in the ſame condition that himſelfe had in it; let theſe men take heede that they doe not fall into the lappe of the whoore of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:12501:7"/>
               <hi>Babylon,</hi> and take her for the church of Chriſt. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whore of <hi>Babylon</hi> hath her glorious viſibilitie in the worlde; ſhee is viſible, &amp; that in great worldly pompe, &amp; glorie. Now the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome will ſay, to what companie, or church the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal I ioyn my ſelf? how ſhal I know, &amp; finde that church, in which I may heare, &amp; receiue the doctrine of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation? yea, if the church be inuiſible, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we cannot ſee it, we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not heare the doctrin therof, we ſhal not come to the true knowledge of GOD to worſhip him, nor yet of our dutie to our king, nor our rulers; nor yet how we are bownde to obeye them. I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere that though the church be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible in that reſpect y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I haue ſpoken off, yet when it commeth in queſtion to what company or church we ſhuld ioyn our ſelues, we haue certein ſure markes to directe vs rightly in this doubt. Theſe markes are, The open,<note place="margin">Markes.</note> and true preaching of the worde of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:12501:8"/>
God; and The ſounde adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the holy Sacramentes; which markes are playne and apparant. Whereſoeuer theſe marks are, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt we are bounde to beleeue that there the true Church is: and that companie wee ought to eſteeme to bee the faithfull Church, which doth profeſſe the religion of the Lord our God, as it is taught in his holy word. Thus the Apoſtle doth call the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie dwelling in <hi>Corinth;</hi> and the <hi>Galathians,</hi> faithfull, and <hi>Sainctes;</hi> and giueth vnto them the name of the Church in generall; although there were amonge them great faultes, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well in ignorance of doctrine, as cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of life. Which thing alſo he taught,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.</note> when hee ſaide that <hi>all they, which did holde the foundation, did not alwayes builde vpon it golde, or ſiluer, or precious ſtones, but alſo ſtubble, and hay.</hi> Thus wee ſpeake of the Church in ſounde, and ſubſtantiall trueth.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:12501:8"/>We doe not make of it a fantaſticall thing, conceiued onely by imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; neither are we carried away in the fonde conceites of the <hi>Donatiſtes,</hi> or <hi>Catharians;</hi> nor in the furious frenſies of the <hi>Anabaptiſtes.</hi> Let mee therefore nowe ſpeake ſomewhat of the marks, &amp; witneſſes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church; which ought well to bee knowne, &amp; marked, becauſe by them we may be directed rightly to that Church, in which ſaluation is to be had. Neither is there any one thing, by which Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than our olde enemie doeth labour more to deceiue men, then by the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, &amp; wrong opinion of the Church. There are two marks, (as I ſaid) moſt certaine, and infallible, by which the true Church is knowne, and diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from all other conuenticles, and aſſemblies of men. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt is, the pure preaching of the worde of God. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond is, the ſincere adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the holy Sacramentes. To
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:12501:9"/>
theſe ſome haue ioyned the true diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, and the fruite of obedience to the goſpell preached. And in truth there ought to be ſuch a chriſtian policie for the gouernement of the church, as the lorde of the church, Chriſt Ieſus hath ordeined; &amp; ſuch obedience ſhewed to the goſpell, as it commaundeth. But becauſe the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounding &amp; force of our ſinnes are ſuch, that often times theſe two laſt things do not ſo fully apeare in their maieſtie, and excellencie, as they ought to doe; therefore we doe reſt our ſelues vpon the two firſt named markes. The preaching of the word is a moſt ſure, and certeine marke, &amp; token of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true church of Chriſt; And therefore the preaching of the goſpell is compared to the ſeede ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen;<note place="margin">Matt. 13.</note> and by the preaching of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, it is ſayd,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 4.</note> that the <hi>Corinthians</hi> were begotten vnto God. For this cauſe alſo is the preaching of the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:12501:9"/>
goſpell called the paſture, in which the children of God do feede; It is the nurriture, with which they are nouriſhed; And Chriſt Ieſus ſayeth, <hi>My ſheepe do heare my voice:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioan. 10.</note> and that they do not heare the voice of a ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. Yea Chriſt teacheth vs how by hearing, and not hearing the worde of God, wee ſhall know them which are of God: For he ſayeth,<note place="margin">Ioan. 8.</note> 
               <hi>He that is of God, heareth Gods words. Ye therefore heare them not, becauſe ye are not of God.</hi> They which are of God, doe heare, receiue, and obey his worde; they are his true church. They which do not heare, nor receiue his worde, are not of God, are not his true church. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond ſure toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the true church, is the ſincere adminiſtration of the holy ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts. For it is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of God, to call, &amp; feed his flock, not onely by the voice of his goſpel, and worde ſounding in their eares, but alſo by mouing their eyes, and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:12501:10"/>
other ſenſes bodily. And therfore he ordeyned that his ſacraments ſhould be certein witneſſes, &amp; viſible ſeales of the vnion of his childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with him ſelfe, &amp; of one of them with another. And this was one cauſe, why it was ſayd to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people of God,<note place="margin">Gen. 17.</note> that he that was vncircumciſed, ſhould be rooted out from among y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people of god. To this end alſo did all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heads of houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds apere at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaſt three times in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yeare before the Lord in <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> to teſtifie by their ſacrifices their vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in faith and religion. Now after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wall of ſeparation was broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> down, which was between the Iewes &amp; the Gentiles; they both, the Iewes (I ſay) &amp; the Gentiles, are brought into one body, not only by the preaching of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one goſpel of Ieſus to them both, but alſo by adminiſtring to them the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, which the lord Ieſus hath ordeyned; that is, Baptiſme, &amp; the ſacrament of his body &amp; bloud.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:12501:10"/>Ieſus ſayde to his Apoſtles:<note place="margin">Matth. 28</note> 
               <hi>Goe teache all nations, baptiſing them in the name of the father, the ſonne, and of the holy Ghoſte.</hi> Here is enioyned both the teaching of the goſpel of Ieſus, &amp; alſo the miniſtring of the ſacrament of Baptiſme. And with the miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of baptiſme, is the adminiſtration of that other ſacrament to be ioined, which S. Paul did alſo ioyne in his miniſterie,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11</note> when he did ſo deliuer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſupper, as he had receiued the ſame of the Lord. Thus is the church grounded vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the foundation of the Prophets, &amp; Apoſtles; that is, euen vpon Ieſus Chriſt him ſelfe, who is the verie ſubſtance of the doctrine Propheticall, and Apoſtolicall. And this is it that S. Paul teacheth, when he ſayeth that <hi>the Church is the piller of the trueth.</hi> For the worde of God,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 3</note> which is the trueth, as Chriſt ſayeth,<note place="margin">Ioan. 17</note> doth ſuſtaine, &amp; vphold the Church, as <hi>Chryſostom</hi> expoundeth that place.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:12501:11"/>And to this purpoſe ſerueth that, which olde father <hi>Irene</hi> writeth:<note place="margin">Iren. lib 3 cap. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumna, &amp; firmamentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Eccleſiae eſt Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelium, &amp; ſpiritus vitae:</hi> The piller, and the buttreſſe of the church, is the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell, and the ſpirite of life. The goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell is the ground, on which the true church is planted and ſet. Likewiſe the church doeth ſtaye it ſelfe onely vpon the worde of God, &amp; is ſtayed by it; without which worde the church could neither be a true chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che of Chriſt, nor be ſtayed in him. By the miniſterie of the church the trueth is ſpread abroad vppon the earth among men. The true church of Chriſt doeth truely teach, &amp; pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh the goſpell of Chriſt, which is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trueth. The trueth &amp; worde of God is placed in the church, as in a ſure &amp; well knowen place. For God doeth by it ſhew his power to ſaue al them which do beleeue.<note place="margin">Rom. 1.</note> Theſe are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the true, and infallible markes of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:12501:11"/>
the church; which is for this cauſe called the mother of the beleeuers, which are engendred, and nouriſhed in it by this true, and vncorrupted paſture, and foode. Nowe if there be the ſaide preaching of the worde of God, and ſyncere adminiſtration of the holy ſacraments, it muſt needs followe, that there are alſo paſtors, and teachers, to whome this charge of teaching &amp; adminiſtration is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted. And this is the cauſe, why ſome haue added to theſe marks this, as a third marke of the church; that is, the ordinarie ſucceſsion of theſe paſtors and miniſters, from the time of the Apoſtles till nowe. In deede ſuch a ſucceſsion is greatly to be li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, regarded, and embraced; but ſo, that this ſucceſsion be rightly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, examined, explicated, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed to the purpoſe. And ſo did many of the auncient fathers ayde them ſelues much againſt the here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:12501:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
which did ſtart vp in their dayes; as <hi>Irene, Tertullian,</hi> and <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stine</hi> did againſt the <hi>Marcionites, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nichees,</hi> and <hi>Donatiſtes.</hi> But becauſe ſome men do vſe this matter of ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsion as a weapon againſt vs, as though we were newe heretikes, &amp; deuiſers of newe doctrines; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you ſhall knowe what wee doe thinke, touching this matter of ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsion.<note place="margin">Succeſſion.</note> We ſaye that there are two kindes of ſucceſsion; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The one is of doctrine; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The other is of perſons. Touching the ſucceſsion of doctrin, we holde that it is an vnfallible rule, and marke of the true church: But as touching the ſucceſsion perſonall, wee do allowe it vppon this condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that it be ioyned with the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Prophets, and Apoſtles in the ſubſtanciall pointes thereof. Wee ſpeake of doctrine, and not of manners. For though there be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in a true paſtor ſound doctrin
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:12501:12"/>
and godly life; yet it may be through ſome ignorance, that a paſtor may fayle in ſome ſuch point of doctrine, as is not a ſubſtantiall point of the doctrine perteining to our ſaluation, whome we will, that notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, accompt as a true paſtor, ſo that he holde the foundation ſure, and ſoundly. Likewiſe, though he doe faile in ſome point of manners, and doe become faultie, yet wee will eſteeme him as a paſtor, and teacher, if he doe teach ſoundly.</p>
            <p>Wee are taught thus to doe by the ſaying of our ſauiour Ieſus Chriſte, who teacheth vs to heare the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes and Phariſees,<note place="margin">Matth. 23.</note> which doe ſit in <hi>Moſes</hi> chaire. Wee muſt doe that which they teache; but we muſt not doe that which they do. Which ſentence,<note place="margin">Tract. 46</note> 
               <hi>Auguſtine</hi> writing vpon the goſpell of Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> openeth thus; That it is to bee vnderſtanded of hyrelings, which do teach ſounde
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:12501:13"/>
doctrine; and that it is not to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanded of falſe teachers. For of them, Chriſt ſayde: Beware of the leauen of the Phariſes. <hi>They which do ſit in Moſes chaire</hi> (ſayth Auguſtine) <hi>do teach the lawe of God; and God doeth teach the people by them: But if they will teach their owne doctrines, heare them not, do not as they teache.</hi> The ſame thing doeth <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in an other place handle; that is, <hi>De verbïs Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni, Serm.</hi> 49. Becauſe falſe teachers may ſucceed the true in the teaching place, and ſo the wolues may ſuccede good ſheapheardes; we do not ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore receiue and allowe all perſonall ſucceſsion. For this kinde of ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion may giue a cloke to falſhod, if the ſucceſsion of doctrin be not ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to it, as the foundation thereof. Moreouer thoſe men, which will holde the ſucceſsion perſonall, ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, and of it ſelfe alone, to be a true, &amp; infallible mark of the true church;
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:12501:13"/>
theſe men muſt ſhewe vs ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of God, by which hee hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to binde his grace to thoſe cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſeates, places, and countries, that in them ſhoulde be ſuch a ſure, and continuall ſucceſſion of holy men, &amp; Biſhoppes ſucceeding one an other.</p>
            <p>This promiſe we finde not in the newe Teſtament. Wee learne there that Chriſte will alwayes haue his chriſtian, catholike, and vniuerſall church; the particular members, and partes whereof are diſperſed, &amp; ſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered abroade throughout the whole vniuerſall worlde; as it pleaſeth God to exerciſe his iudgementes vppon them, whome either he cutteth off for euer, or on them whome he doth chaſtice, and afflict for a time, and to enlarge his mercies vpon them, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hee leadeth from good to better; or that hee doeth call ſome of them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newe to the true knowledge of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. For ſometimes the Lord God
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:12501:14"/>
ſhewing foorth his iuſt vengeaunce, doeth ſo caſt downe, and cutt of all, that hee will not leaue ſo much as a trace of his true church in a place; as ſometimes he did in <hi>Iurie;</hi> and is in our time come to paſſe in <hi>Barbarie.</hi> In ſome other place he doth ſo deſtroy, that yet hee leaueth there ſome little trace, and token of a church; as now we may ſee in al <hi>Graecia,</hi> and in ſome other places alſo more neare to vs. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Sometimes alſo the Lorde doeth cut off the perſonal ſucceſſion of Paſtors, by the fault, corruption, negligence, and ſluggiſhneſſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Paſtors them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> or by ſuch violence, as is vſed againſt thoſe paſtors which are good <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Of the firſte wee may take example of the church of <hi>Antioche,</hi> in which <hi>Samoſatenus</hi> an euill heretike did tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe corruption and ouerſight ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede good fathers going before him. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Of the ſeconde, the church of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria</hi> may giue vs an example; out
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:12501:14"/>
of which, when good <hi>Athanaſius</hi> was baniſhed, <hi>Arians</hi> did ſucceed. The like is to be ſeene alſo in moe other chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, by him that will marke the hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories of the church. Such a cutting off, and breaking of perſonall ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion was euen in the church of <hi>Rome,</hi> more than once or twiſe; As when <hi>Honorius</hi> the firſt of that name, being Pope, and Biſhoppe there, was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned for partaking with the hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible hereſie of <hi>Eutiches,</hi> about the yeare of our Lorde 623. And when <hi>Iohn,</hi> the xxii. of that name, was by a general cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned for hereſie. Likewiſe was the perſonal ſucceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cut off in <hi>Rome,</hi> when y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Pope,<note place="margin">Anno Do. 854.</note> whom in her popedome, they called <hi>Iohn,</hi> who before was called <hi>Agnes,</hi> was Biſhoppe of <hi>Rome;</hi> as <hi>Ioannes Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſis Epiſcopus</hi> doeth report in his booke intituled <hi>Onus Eccleſiae.</hi> So was it cutt off alſo in the perſon of <hi>Silueſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> the ſeconde; and of <hi>Gregorie</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:12501:15"/>
the ſeuenth; and in a number of ſuch necromanticall Popes. Likewiſe it was cut off in the times of the romiſh ſchiſmes; and when ſchiſmaticall Popes, who were in thoſe ſchiſmes, helde the helme, and did ſit (as they ſay) in <hi>Peters</hi> chaire; when Pope was againſt Pope, euen in <hi>Rome;</hi> &amp; one Pope curſing an other Pope; chalen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to each of them <hi>Peters</hi> chaire, &amp; that for the ſpace of many yeares. And ſometimes they all, that thus chalenged, were turned out of the ſeat of <hi>Rome,</hi> and that by decree of a generall councel; As at <hi>Conſtance</hi> three Popes were vnpoped at once; and at <hi>Baſill</hi> one. This proueth ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the of cutting of the perſonall ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion in the Popes, and Biſhoppes of <hi>Rome.</hi> To this alſo may be added the tragedies, which Pope played a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Pope, from the time of pope <hi>Formoſus,</hi> which was about the yeare 893. vntill the time of Pope <hi>Leo,</hi> the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:12501:15"/>
viii. of that name. The wiſe reader ſhal eaſily perceiue how Pope ſought to cutt off Pope, both in perſon and proceedings; one condemning that which an other had decreed; beſides cruelties exerciſed on the bodyes of ſome of them being deade. This ſchiſme in the church of <hi>Rome</hi> is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted haue bene verie long, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with moſt cruell. So that if there were want of other helpes, the Popes themſelues haue holpen vs plentiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to ſee how the perſonall ſucceſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath beene cut off by Popes themſelues. The cruel, and popelike tragedies in <hi>Rome</hi> doe ſo diſpleaſe the Papiſtes them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, that one of them,<note place="margin">Faſcicul. temp.</note> writing the hiſtory of this time, burſteth out into this exclamation: <hi>O moſt curſed times!</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nauclet. to. 2.</note> And one other hath it in horror, to report howe many things were wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly done by no fewer tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 28. popes, one ſucceeding an other. Let the godly
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:12501:16"/>
reader alſo wey what cutting of ther was of this perſonall ſucceſsion, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pott of poyſon, Pope after pope was cutt off by that cunning poyſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner <hi>Brazutus;</hi> which yet at the length, made ſome ſtay in one of the worſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euer did ſit at <hi>Rome, Gregorie</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth; as no leſſe man of credite than a Cardinall doth write.<note place="margin">Beno.</note> So that, if either cutting off perſons, or cutting off the doctrines, &amp; degres of popes, may bee taken to bee a cutting off the perſonall ſucceſſion in <hi>Rome,</hi> then was it cutt off many yeares ſince. Therefore without looking to this perſonal ſucceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which doth ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and by many occaſions faile, a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly chriſtian may full well know the true church of Chriſt. And ſo ſhall he doe, if hee will obſerue when, and where the true doctrine of God is taught, and the ſyncere adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the holy Sacramentes is obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. They are to be taken for the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:12501:16"/>
of the Apoſtles, which being lawefully called to this miniſterie, do build vpon the foundation of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and doe enter into their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours; whether they haue among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a perſonal ſucceſſion in perpetui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, or y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it hath bene cut off for a time; or that themſelues bee the firſt that preach the Goſpell in the place to which they are called to exerciſe the office of a true miniſter of Chriſtes church. And on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> contrary part, thoſe paſtors in place, which do not preach the goſpell of God at all; or which, in ſteade of preaching the doctrine of the Apoſtles, do preach their own doctrine by themſelues inuented; though they doe alleadge a thouſand of their predeceſſors, which folowed one an other in perſonall ſucceſſion, yet are they not to bee taken for true paſtors, but are wolues, and ſo to be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; neither are they, nor can they be reputed, nor taken to bee the true
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:12501:17"/>
paſtors of Chriſts church, how larg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſoeuer they account of perſonall ſucceſsion. His worde is not in their mouthes; neither are the congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which are miſſeled with ſuch wolues, to bee taken to bee the true church of Chriſt. For the true church of Chriſt doeth not heare the voyce of a ſtranger. But this miſſeled church doeth both heare, and receiue the voyce of a ſtraunger, and ſtraunge doctrines; They haue not the worde of Chriſt taught; They wil not heare it, neither will they haue his holy Sacramentes ſyncerely adminiſtred to them. If any man wil aske whether it be lawful for euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wil, of his own priuate authoritie to preach the goſpell, &amp; to miniſter the holy ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes; I aunſwere, no truely: For all thinges in the houſe of God muſt be done in good and comely order, as the Apoſtle doth teach vs.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 14.</note> Who then (will you ſay) are the verie true
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:12501:17"/>
paſtors, and teachers? Euen they, which are lawfully called to that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and doe it faithfully. Now then we muſt knowe, what a lawfull cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling is. There is a forme,<note place="margin">Of calling</note> or maner of calling ordinarie: Ther is alſo a form or maner of calling extraordinarie. That is rightly ordinarie, in which that order is obſerued, which God hath eſtabliſhed in his worde and church. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> In this order is firſt right aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning of men to do the office truly; to which by the worde of God they are called. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Then a triall muſt be had of their habilitie in doctrine, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination of life. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Then a lawfull e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, or chooſing; Laſt of all fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth the impoſition of handes. This is to be ſeene by the example of the practiſe of the Apoſtles them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. For ſo was <hi>Mathias</hi> choſen, So were y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Deacons</hi> choſen: And here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to do thoſe rules ſerue, which S. Paul doth giue in his Epiſtles write<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothie</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:12501:18"/>
and to <hi>Titus,</hi> touching the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of church miniſters. You ſee nowe what the ordinarie calling is; out of which we may eaſily gather, what the extraordinary calling, or vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation is; which hauing an authoritie from God is lawfull, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that one, or two pointes, apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayning to an ordinarie calling, bee wanting in it. The Lord hath often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times vſed the ſeruice of men called to the miniſterie of the word, by ſuch an extraordinary calling, as appeareth by the holy ſcriptures. <hi>Moſes</hi> had no ordinarie calling by men. <hi>Iirmiah, Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas</hi> had none. <hi>Daniel, Amos,</hi> and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe other of the Prophetes, had no ordinarie calling by men; and yet the Lord God called theſe men, &amp; ſuch like, to the miniſterie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they which kept the place of the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary calling, did abuſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (I ſay) then God vſed to lay to his hand extraordinarily to the worke,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:12501:18"/>
which they that had their ordinarie calling, did not onely neglecte, but bring into ruine. Thus the Lord god himſelf did; and yet he did not bring any diſorder, or confuſion into his houſe by this meane: But thus did he to correct, and reforme, that confuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; diſorder, which was brought into his houſe, by them, which, vnder the colour of ordinarie ſucceſſion, did o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowe all good order, &amp; peruer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it. This doth the writings of the prophets witnes, in which the prieſts are chiefely reproued. If you will ſay that the men, whome the Lorde did thus call extraordinarily, had yet ſome outwarde, &amp; miraculous teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of this their heauenly calling; It is ſo in deed of ſome; but it was not ſo in all. I doe not finde that many of the Prophets did come of the race of <hi>Aaron;</hi> nor that the ordinarie im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of handes was layde vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon them; Nor that they teſtified
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:12501:19"/>
their vocation, and calling, by wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſtraung ſignes, and miracles. If you will ſay that theſe prophetes, &amp; teachers, which had this extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie calling, did content themſelues with that part of the church office, which is to teach, and to reprooue; but they did not meddle with the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices; This is not altogether true. For <hi>Samuel</hi> who was not of the ſtock of <hi>Aaron,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 7.</note> did ſacrifice in <hi>Mizpah,</hi> as it is written. And <hi>Eliah</hi> beeing a <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laadite,</hi> did ſacrifice in <hi>Carmel.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Reg. 18.</note> Again, it is no maruel, if the prophets of that time did not extende their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of their extraordinary cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, to circumciſe, and ſacrifice; for that was the charge, and priuiledge then expreſſely committed to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtock of <hi>Leui</hi> for that time. Thus you heare what is the church, and what bee the markes thereof, and what is to bee thought of the vocation, or calling of the Paſtors and teachers of the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:12501:19"/>
church. And thus doe wee at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent approue our chriſtian church, &amp; the miniſters thereof by the rule of Gods word.<note place="margin">Tom. 4. fol. 160.</note> And in this behalfe doth that make for vs, which <hi>Auguſtine</hi> writeth in his booke of 65. queſtions, and in the laſt queſtion; where he tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth, that wee ſhall knowe that he is ſent of God, who is not choſen by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> flatterie of a fewe men; but he, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> life, good manners, and the doing of the Apoſtolike Prieſts do commend; who ſeeketh not to be aloft, but to be profitable to others.<note place="margin">Of the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of the church</note> Nowe let vs come to the authoritie of the church, and ſpeake a little thereof. It doth appeare by that which is ſaid before, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wee do not take away any thing of thoſe high, and glorious titles, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che the holy ghoſt doeth giue vnto it. We ſay, that it is the body of Chriſt; but ſo, that part thereof is yet in pilgrimage, looking for the full in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioying of the heade Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:12501:20"/>This is the houſe of God, which hee doth dayly builde, ſo that it groweth ſtil more and more. It is gouerned by the ſpirit of God, ſtil fighting againſt the fleſhe. It is purified, but ſo that it is by little and little brought towards that perfection of beauty, in which is neither blemiſh nor I pot. It knoweth God truely, but yet in part. In which kinde of ſpeaches, I doe vſe the very wordes of the holy ſcripture. Out of this Church is no ſaluation: For life and ſaluation is no where elſe but in Chriſt Ieſus alone, and onely; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doeth the Lorde Ieſus powre foorth his quickning power, &amp; grace, but onely vpon his owne members. The vnion and aſſembling of them together in their head Ieſus, is called, and is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true church of Chriſt. If you aske me whether this church being in this worlde, can erre; and whether it be in authority aboue the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or elſe it be ſubiecte to the holy
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:12501:20"/>
word of God;<note place="margin">Howe the Church may erre.</note> To the firſt I anſwere that it is out of doubt, that the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the church, counting each one by himſelfe in particular, may erre; And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there are of them, which do erre in doctrine &amp; maners of life. For <hi>they knowe but in part,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 13.</note> as S. Paul ſaith. And <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">1. Iohn. 1.</note> 
               <hi>If we do ſay that we haue no ſinne, we do deceiue our ſelues:</hi> And in this number we may, and do recken the olde doctors. For many faultes are to be founde in them; and therefore they are not to be receiued in al things without exception. Thus doe we thinke of the members of the church in particular; whoſe imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections doe not ſo prevaile, but that of them knitte together in trueth, is made a true church. For they do by little and little growe, and goe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde in the knowledge of God, and of his trueth, and holineſſe of life. But if wee will conſider the partes of the Church more generally,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:12501:21"/>
as it is diuided into diuerſe Dioceſſes, and Prouinces, we ſay playnely that it may erre.<note place="margin">Card. Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha.</note> It is alſo confeſſed by one of the chiefe capitaines ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for the Pope his Lorde, that particular churches, and prouinciall Synodes may erre, and haue often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times erred. Which thing long ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience hath prooued true. Let vs then conſider the church in the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſalitie thereof, which is (as ſome ſay) conſidered in that it is in a generall councell repreſented. There is no cauſe why we ſhoulde thinke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all the power, and giftes which the holy ghoſt doeth beſtowe vpon the vniuerſall church, ſhoulde be reſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to a certaine number of prelates, gathered together in a generall coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, which are not alwayes the beſt learned, nor the beſt men which are in the whole chuch, although they doe there repreſent the whole multitude of them, which did ſende
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:12501:21"/>
them thither. For it falleth out of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten times that a ſimple man ſhalbe founde to haue better vnderſtanding than the greateſt man in the whole aſſembly.<note place="margin">Panormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan.</note> Which cauſed one fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous <hi>Canoniſt</hi> to write vppon the chapter <hi>Significaſti, tit. de Electionibus,</hi> that ſometime more credite is to be giuen to one priuate man, beeing a faithfull man, and who hath on his ſide better authoritie &amp; reaſon, than is to be giuen to the whole Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, or to the Pope him ſelfe. And in that great, and firſt Councel of <hi>Nice,</hi> it was long of one poore <hi>Paphnutius</hi> that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe of ſole life, which ſince y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> time hath brought much filthineſſe into the church, was not then eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed. Againe, when ſhall there ſo generall a Councell be aſſembled, in which a great number of learned, &amp; holy men, are not left out of the Councell? And who can aſſure vs, but that they, which are abſent, may
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:12501:22"/>
not ſometime haue more vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of a trueth, than they all, which are preſent at the Councell? It is alſo wel known how long time now an horrible confuſion hath reigned in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church, &amp; that chiefely in the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt dignitie of the prelacie. So that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greateſt deſolation in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſe of god hath ben, &amp; is, by the means of them, by whome it ſhould haue been beſt furniſhed. Which hath cauſed ſome biſhops &amp; churchmen to caſt foorth many grieuous ſighes, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaints, moſt cleare, and ſo lowde, that wee do yet heare the ſound of them. It is knowne alſo that complaints hereof haue paſſed the penne of the Pope himſelfe at ſometimes,<note place="margin">Pope Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drian. 6.</note> &amp; haue ſlip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped out of the mouthes of Popiſh Biſhops at many times; as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bookes of the Councels doe teſtifie. <hi>Bernard</hi> alſo in his bookes of <hi>Conſideration,</hi> &amp; in his ſermon, which he made vpon the conuerſion of ſaint <hi>Paul,</hi> ſpeaketh
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:12501:22"/>
both openly and truely; <hi>Alas Lorde</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>they, which do loue the first, &amp; chiefe places in the church, and to beare the chiefe rule in it, are the firſt which do perſecute thee. They haue taken the Arke of Sion; they haue taken the castell, and afterward haue ſet the whole citie on fire.</hi> By this wee may ſee that they which then had the higheſt, and moſt prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall places in the church, were farre out of order. The ſame men doe holde and will holde the ſame places ſtill. Now ſurely the generall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time, which were, &amp; haue ben gathered of ſuch perſons, ſo euill qualified, haue not ben ſo conducted by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ghoſt, but that they might erre. And euen ſo the whole vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie of <hi>Paris</hi> did think, &amp; iudge of the Councell holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at <hi>Rome</hi> by Pope <hi>Leo</hi> the tenth of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name; &amp; therfore they apealed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, &amp; his ſaid Councel. Againe, if a generall Councell hath receyued this priuiledge, that it can
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:12501:23"/>
not erre in doctrine, let vs knowe of what date this priuiledge is, and when it was giuen. There was yet neuer but one true faith; But there haue beene many errours. For euen in the church, which was in the olde teſtament, the Prophets doe tell vs plainly, and the hiſtories of that time do proue, that there were errours, and foule faults among them, which ſhould haue beene the teachers of the trueth.<note place="margin">Iſay. 56.10</note> 
               <hi>All their watchmen (ſayth the Prophete I ſay) are blinde; they knowe not thing;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iirm. 6.13</note> 
               <hi>they are all dumme dogges.</hi> The Prophet <hi>Iirmiah</hi> ſayth, <hi>From the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet to the Prieſt, all do deale falſely.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And becauſe theſe reproofes ſhould not be reſtrained to the particular liues and manners of men, he ſayeth plainly,<note place="margin">Iir. 14.14.</note> 
               <hi>They do propheſie falſe things, &amp; a lying viſion.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai 29.14</note> Againe, <hi>Iſay</hi> ſayth, <hi>that the wiſedome of the wiſe ſhall periſh, and the vnderſtanding of the prowde ſhall va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh: and that God will ſtop the eyes of the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:12501:23"/>
Prophets, euen of the chiefe of them.</hi> The Prophet <hi>Ezechiel</hi> ſayeth,<note place="margin">Ezech. 7.</note> 
               <hi>that the lawe ſhall periſh through the Prieſt;</hi> that is, <hi>through the fault of the Prieſt.</hi> And in deede who did condemne the true Prophets, and ſeruants of the liuing God <hi>Iirmiah, Micheah,</hi> and other; yea, euen the verie ſonne of God him ſelf, and after him his Apoſtles? who did this, but the aſſemblies, &amp; Councels of the prelats, which were in thoſe dayes? If you will ſaye, Theſe things happened in the olde Teſtament; that cannot warrant our times.<note place="margin">2. Pet. 2.</note> For firſt the time of the newe Teſtament is not priuiledged from hauing of ſuch falſe teachers. Saint <hi>Peter</hi> telleth vs plainly that, <hi>as there were falſe Prophets in the olde time, ſo there ſhould be in the time after him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Furthermore of the time of the newe Teſtament S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh plainly,<note place="margin">Act. 20.</note> that, <hi>euen in our time of the newe Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Wolues ſhall come out of the midſt
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:12501:24"/>
of the paſtors.</hi> And in another place, <hi>That the child of perdition ſhall ſit in the temple of God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 2.</note> And in conferring the Councelles together, the one with the other, wee ſhall finde ſuch contrarieties in them, that it will eaſily appeare, that they did not alwayes heare, and obey the holy ghoſt; but that Satan tranſforming him ſelfe into the forme of an Angel of light, hath ruled, and ouerruled in ſome generall Councels:<note place="margin">Aug. lib. 2. de baptiſ. contra Donatiſt. cap. 31.</note> 
               <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, that the Epiſtles of particular Biſhoppes are corrected by prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall Councels; and that prouinciall Councels are corrected by the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, The former amended by the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; when as by more experience had of things, that, which was before ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, and vnknowen, is made more knowen; and that which was hidden, is brought to light. Neither is this rule to be reſtrained to ſuch exterior things as may be altered, &amp; changed,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:12501:24"/>
as the neceſsitie of the time doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire. This worde <hi>(Emendari)</hi> which <hi>Auguſtine</hi> doeth vſe, preſuppoſeth a fault committed, and afterwarde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, be it in doctrine or maners. And <hi>Auguſtine</hi> doth not ſpeake there of any external policie, but of a point of doctrine; that is of the opinion of <hi>Ciprian,</hi> &amp; of the Councel of <hi>Afrique,</hi> touching rebaptiſing. If you wil ſay, that our Sauiour Ieſus hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> midſt of two, or three, which are gathered together in his name; therfore he wil be in the midſt of a general Councel; This may wel be preſumed; but there is a difference between a preſumption, &amp; a neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry concluſion. For ſince the malice of men proceedeth ſo farre often times, euen to abuſe the moſt holy name of God to fortifie falſhod; ſuch me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may haue God in their mouth, which are his enimies in their hearts.</p>
            <p>The weakneſſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnderſtanding
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:12501:25"/>
of men is ſuch, that it is often ſeene howe corrupt affections do blinde their eyes, and mindes, ſo that hee which hath none other foundation, but the aduiſe of men, is more often in danger to be deceiued, than other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. Is then the doctrine of the church vncerteine? (will ye ſaye) or can the church erre? Of the erring of the church I haue alreadie ſpoken, therfore vnto the firſt queſtion I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere thus. The doctrine which the Lorde our God hath deliuered to be the doctrine of his church, is moſte certeine and ſure. But becauſe men do yet knowe but in parte, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſayeth; in this reſpect ſomtime errour is mingled with the trueth in the knowledge of men. This is true, that the Lorde our God will not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer that the ſubſtantiall pointes of trueth, touching our ſaluation, ſhall alwayes be buryed in the whole church; but the Lord will haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:12501:25"/>
ſome number in it, ſometime litle, ſometime great, which ſhal vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand that, which they ought to vnderſtande; and follow that, which they ought to followe. So did it come to paſſe in the time of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Eliah</hi> in <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and in the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuitie of <hi>Babylon;</hi> and alſo in the time of the comming of our ſauiour Chriſt. For euen then was founde a number, though but a litle number of them, whoſe hearts were touched with the knowledge and taſte of trueth; as <hi>Zacharie, Elizabeth, Iohn the Baptiſt, Ioſeph,</hi> the <hi>virgin Marie, Simeon, Anna.</hi> Theſe did knowe, and had the right, and ſure vnderſtanding of the certein fulfilling of the prophecies of the comming of the promiſed Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our. And yet they liued in the midſt of the corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the Scribes, Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees, Sadduces, &amp; prieſtes. Such in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terruptions of open profeſsing the trueth, happen in the church of God,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:12501:26"/>
proceeding of the iniquitie of men, as a thick miſt, which after vaniſheth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way by the heat of the Sunne of the doctrine; I meane of the worde of God; when it pleaſeth God, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his ſecrete ordinance, iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp; wiſedome, to ſuffer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame Sunne of his worde to ſhine foorth with power, &amp; maieſtie, then trueth is ſeen, embraced, &amp; profeſſed of the elect children of God. Thinke you now y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we will, or that we doe reiect al the old Councels? Nay verily; but this I ſay, that, if all the rules giuen in the eldeſt &amp; beſt of them, were put in execution at this daye, they woulde make a greater change in the popiſh or Romiſh church (called catholike) than they would or could doe in the church, which is nowe reformed by the goſpell of Ieſus. But let the holy word of God be the toucheſtone, to trye &amp; examine all that is ſayde, or done in the church, and then it will
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:12501:26"/>
be eaſily ſeene where the true church is. Count not this a ſtraunge thing that I require; For it is an olde ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, receiued before our times, of the moſt catholike doctors.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Auguſtine</hi> writing to <hi>Maximinus</hi> the <hi>Arrian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Li. 2. ca. 14</note> Is there any generall Councell more allowed or appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued than that firſt Councell, which was holden at <hi>Nice?</hi> I trowe not (ſayeth he.) And what is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell which was holden at <hi>Ariminum?</hi> It was a Councell reiected, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned for good cauſe. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> there handleth a principall point of our Chriſtian faith; that is, the diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of Chriſt our Lord, &amp; Sauiour; And yet <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> for his part, he wil not be bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Nicene</hi> coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell; neither wil he haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Aria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> bound to the Councell holden at <hi>Ariminum;</hi> but he wil haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matter tried by the holy ſcriptures, which are the mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt witneſſes for both partes. It
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:12501:27"/>
may be that theſe Romiſh me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which doe runne away from the ſcriptures, will ſay that there is great darkneſſe in the holy ſcripture. I anſwere that it is moſt true, which ſaint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, that <hi>the naturall man perceiueth not the thinges of the ſpirite of God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 2.</note> It is true al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that ſaint <hi>Peter</hi> ſayth,<note place="margin">2. Pet. 1.</note> that <hi>no prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie in the ſcripture is of any priuate inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation.</hi> But yet this obſcuritie is not ſo great, but that the ſcriptures can expound them ſelues. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doeth our Lord, and chiefe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Ieſus, ſend vs to the ſcriptures, &amp; to nothing elſe but to the ſcriptures. <hi>Search you the ſcriptures</hi> (ſayth he.<note place="margin">Ioan. 5. Luc. 16.</note>) <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> beeing required by the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned rich man to ſende ſome one fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the dead, to admoniſh his brethren, which yet liued in his old houſe, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered thus, <hi>They haue</hi> (ſayth <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham) Moſes, and the Prophets; If they will not beleeue them, they will not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue any that ſhall come to them from the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:12501:27"/>
dead.</hi> And howe did all thoſe moſte auncient and godly Chriſtians be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs, which had among them on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the ſcriptures of the Prophets, and Apoſtles, before that any commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie, or explication was written vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon any of them by the olde writers? did they not then fetche all their light of the holy ſcripture onely? A Romiſh man will here drawe vs to receiue the traditions Apoſtolicall for a moſte ſure interpretation of the holy ſcripture;<note place="margin">Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> And by Apoſtolicall traditions, he wil meane that, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <hi>which hath beene always receiued in the church; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> through all the church; and by them all, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> which haue beene of the church.</hi> But nowe who can aſſure vs, that theſe three pointes are to be founde in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of theſe traditions, which they do call Apoſtolicall traditions? I doe not knowe who can doe it. There is great diuerſitie to be founde in the bookes, and writings of the auncient
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:12501:28"/>
fathers; and that in ſome pointes touching faith. And againe, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching theſe wordes <hi>(alwayes)</hi> and <hi>(of all)</hi> let the Romiſh men tell vs, at what time wee ſhall begin the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of this <hi>(alwayes.)</hi> If wee will do well, wee muſt fetch the beginning of this time euen at the church Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolike. And who ſhall be the firſte in this account? verily the Apoſtles them ſelues muſt be the firſt that ſhal begin this account; the hiſtorie of whome is faithfully written by S. <hi>Luke;</hi> and by their owne writings wee muſt take knowledge of them, their doctrine and their doings? All trueth commeth of God; And God hath choſen his Prophets, and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles to ſpeake in his name vnto vs all that trueth, which doeth apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to our ſaluation. Therefore wee muſt alwayes haue, and make our recourſe to the holy ſcriptures. And yet wee doe not vtterly caſt
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:12501:28"/>
away the aduice of Councels, nor of the auncient fathers. Wee doe proue that, which they do ſaye, by the holy ſcriptures. The which ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſcriptures (as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> doeth ſaye truely) are ſo tempered by the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpirite of God, that that, which is obſcurely ſpoken in one place, is clearely expreſſed in another place of them.</p>
            <p>Some of the Romiſh rout haue ſayd, that the whole wil of God, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching all that, which doeth apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to our ſaluation, is not all writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by the Apoſtles and Euangeliſts. By this wicked, &amp; falſe ſaying, they make an open way to bring in al that falſehood, error, &amp; vntrueth, which men liſt to deuiſe. And it is the way, by which, Satan hath entred to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the vineyard of the Lorde, to ſowe therein his darnell of damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and cockle, choking true do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and Chriſtian faith.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:12501:29"/>I graunt that before the time of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> God gouerned his church by hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly viſions, inſpirations, and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations; But the Apoſtles planted the churches of God by his holy worde written. And the malice of men gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing with the number of them; and the better ſort of men decaying to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with goodnes, it was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good pleaſure of the Lorde our God, that this doctrine ſhoulde be written in a tongue common, and knowen, by which plaine trueth, Gods children might receiue all that doctrin, which concerneth ſaluation, and might al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo withſtand all ſubtilties creeping in vnder the couler of traditions, or reuelations, or cuſtome, or other de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of man whatſoeuer. Now if the doctrine of our ſaluation were writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten but in parte; how ſhal we do for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſt which is wanting? Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> doth not ſpeake ſo ſcantly of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſcriptures, as theſe Romiſh me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do.
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:12501:29"/>
For he ſaith that the thinges,<note place="margin">Ioan. 20.</note> which hee hath written, are written to this ende, that we beleeuing them, might haue life; that is, ſaluation, for that is life indeede. Then is there no other doctrine neceſſarie to ſaluation, but that, which is written in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; And that which is written in the holy ſcriptures, ſuffiſeth vnto ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. Saint Paul teaching vs what the vſe of the ſcripture is; teaching vs all (I ſay) in the perſon of his ſcho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler <hi>Timothie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.</note> ſaith <hi>that they doe make the man of God</hi> (not onely euery faithful miniſter &amp; Paſtor, but euery faithful man) <hi>perfect and fully perfited.</hi> Then a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nedeth not any vnwritten verity, or traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (as they are called) Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>like. Yet I do not deny but that there haue beene alwayes vnwritten tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, touching order, and manner of doing in the church; but not ſo in poyntes of doctrine touching faith and ſaluation. Nowe becauſe men
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:12501:30"/>
haue long time abuſed the name of tradition, we muſt learne to knowe which are traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to be allowed, &amp; receiued; and which are not to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed. This is eaſie to be done, if we will ſet before vs ſome pointes, &amp; by them frame our iudgement. Firſt we muſt put a iuſt difference betwen do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and matter of rites, and orders of the church. In doctrine the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles deliuered, in the worde by them written, onely, and wholy all that which they had rceiued of the Lord. To this then I adde, that if the tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions offered to vs, be agreeable to the worde of God; and are meete, and fit for edifying, then are they to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued. For this is a thing aſſured, that niether the Apoſtles, nor the true Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, did appoynt any orders, or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of doing, which were either di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly, or indirectly contrarie to the doctrine of the goſpell; nor ſuch as ſhould turne any man neuer ſo little
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:12501:30"/>
from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeruice of God, which is ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual. This being obſerued of vs, it ſhal be eaſie for vs to diſcerne the doctrin fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> traditions, and the falſe traditions fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the true. It was accompted with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> old father. <hi>Tertullian</hi> a very ſtraunge thing, that any man ſhould ſay that he had omitted to teach any thing (ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by word of mouth, or by wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting) of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which doth apertain to our ſaluation. I will ſay further, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all that, which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtles did deliuer as tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, in matter of order, rites, &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of doing, are not to be kept per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually. For according to the rule of charitie they ordeined touching the ſtrangled, &amp; not to eat blood;<note place="margin">Act. 15.29.</note> confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming their tradition herein to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie of the Iewes. Some like thing may be noted in the doings of S. Paul in the perſon of <hi>Timothie;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act 16.3.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Act. 18.18</note> yea and in him ſelfe alſo; which thinges can haue no place at this day, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in this, that the generall rule
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:12501:31"/>
muſt be obſerued, that wee muſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply ourſelues to the commoditie, &amp; profite of our neighbour, in thoſe thinges which are indifferent. The like thinges may bee gathered tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the traditions and manners of doing, which they applyed to their time; As where he ſpeketh of kiſſing; and of hauing the heade vncouered in ſigne of authoritie;<note place="margin">1. Cor. 16. 1. Cor. 11.</note> which are thinges contrarie to the manner of doinges in theſe dayes in many cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, where men woulde count it ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſtraunge, that men ſhoulde kiſſe one an other; or that a man ſhould kiſſe any woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, other than his own wife. And alſo to ſpeake at this day with the head bare, and vncouered, is a ſigne, and token of ſubiection &amp; not of authoritie. All theſe thinges are well to be conſidered, before wee doe receiue any cuſtome, or tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as Apoſtolike. For the name of the Apoſtles is not to bee abuſed to
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:12501:31"/>
trouble the Church in any thing; as it was abuſed in the controuerſie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the keeping of the day of the <hi>Paſque,</hi> which wee call <hi>Eaſter;</hi> And likwiſe when ſome abuſed the name of the Apoſtles, and the authoritie of the Church of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Actes. 15.</note> labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring vnder this pretence to mingle <hi>Iudaiſme</hi> with <hi>Chriſtianiſme,</hi> as it is written in the Actes of the Apoſtles: There it was ordeined that the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of men ſhoulde not be char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with any ſuch yoke. Wee can not thinke therfore that the Apoſtles did inuent ſo many ceremonies, as are nowe vſed; in the obſeruation of which is ſet the forgiuenes of ſinnes, and merites. For they haue plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proteſted the contrarie; neither woulde they giue place to the cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of <hi>Moſes,</hi> of which God him ſelfe was the author. Long agoe did <hi>Auguſtine</hi> complayne of the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of ceremonies,<note place="margin">Ep. ad Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuarium.</note> and humayne
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:12501:32"/>
traditions brought into the Church. But what would he haue ſaide, if hee had liued in ſuch a time as ours is? To be ſhort therefore, we do require that the holy ſcriptures, which are in this point moſt plain &amp; cleare, may guide vs to diſcerne betweene the traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s which are good, and which are badd; holy, and prophane; hurtful, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable; neceſſarie, and ſuperfluous. Theſe thinges being decided, it ſhall be eaſie to determine this queſtion touching traditions; and ſo wee may come to touch a ſeconde queſtion, which is dropped downe to vs from <hi>Rome;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Whether the church be aboue the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</note> that is, whether the church bee aboue the ſcriptures; which is as vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>handſome a queſtion, as if one ſhould aske, whether the child be aboue the father; the ſcholer aboue the ſchole-maſter; the wife aboue the husbande, or man aboue God. But indeede the true church of Chriſt will not in this matter make any quarrel againſt god.
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:12501:32"/>
For if it ſhoulde, it ſhoulde fall in the quarrell, and be condemned. It is to no purpoſe, to ſay that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church was before the ſcriptures. For though it were ſo, yet the word of God is more auncient than the church. For by the worde the Church is conceiued, engendred, made, &amp; named y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church. That which doeth ingender, is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the thing that is ingendred; as the father, and mother are, and haue their beeing before the childe. Some will alleadge, the ſaying of <hi>Auguſtine, I ſhoulde not beleeue the ſcriptures, if the authoritie of the Church did not moue me.</hi> In that place <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeaketh of himſelfe, as he was when he was a <hi>Manichee.</hi> When two contrary parts ſhal fal into debate touching the truth of an Inſtrument, or writing, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall they haue recourſe, but to the Notarie, which keepeth the recorde? But yet it will not bee ſaide that the writinge is grounded vppon
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:12501:33"/>
the authoritie of the Notarie, for that the recorde is true, although no man liuing doe beare witneſſe thereof. So I aunſwere them, which doe thinke that the holy ſcripture is not other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe founded, but vppon the deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of the church. This veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly were a feeble, &amp; a ſlender ground. For we ſhal find y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> determinations of councells, which are called the church repreſentatiue, one contrarie to an other; as by conference of them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether it will appeare. Herevnto I will adde this reaſon, Ieſus Chriſte is hee, whome all the true Prophetes honoured (for as their Lorde he did ſend the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) and yet they are not aboue him, but he aboue them, notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding he doth approue his doctrin by their teſtimonies. S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſuffereth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Bereites</hi> to do y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> like with his doctrin.<note place="margin">Act. 17.</note> S. <hi>Peter</hi> prayſeth greatly this kinde of doing.<note place="margin">2. Pet. 1.19.</note> Therefore they, which doe call themſelues the Vicars of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:12501:33"/>
Chriſt, &amp; the ſucceſſors of Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> may not refuſe this condition. To this purpoſe ſerueth that, which <hi>Hierome</hi> writeth; <hi>We muſt not</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>followe the errours of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, nor of aunceſtours; But wee muſt follow the authorite of the holy ſcriptures.</hi> And <hi>Chryſostome</hi> writing vppon the 14.<note place="margin">Lib. 2. in lir. cap. 9.</note> chapter of the goſpell of Sainte <hi>Mathewe,</hi> ſaith: <hi>That hee, which will knowe which is the true Church of Chriſt, when thinges are in confuſion through likelihoode, hee muſt knowe it by the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</hi> And in the ſame place vppon theſe wordes:<note place="margin">Hom. 49.</note> 
               <hi>(Let them, which are in Iurie, flee vnto the mountaines)</hi> he ſaith, <hi>Let them, which are in the christianitie, retire, and drawe them ſelues to the holy ſcriptures. For when the time is ſuch, that hereſie doeth poſſeſſe the Churches ſo, that one cannot haue by; or in the church, any ſure or certaine tryall, to prooue which is true chriſtianitie, there can bee no other refuge to ſuch chriſtians, as are deſirous
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:12501:34"/>
of the chriſtian faith, but only to the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</hi> whoſoeuer then will not know which is the true church of Chriſte, how ſhal he know it, but only by the holy ſcriptures? (ſaith this ancient fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.) Againe he ſaith, <hi>The Lord know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that great confuſion ſhould come in the later dayes, doth commaund that the chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, which doe deſire to take ſome holde of true faith, ſhould haue their refuge to nothing, but to the holy ſcriptures. For o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe if they will haue regard to other thinges, they ſhall be offended, and periſhe, not vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding which is the true church; and ſo ſhall fall into the abhomination of deſolation, which wil hold it ſelf in the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly place of the Church.</hi> An other olde greek writer (<hi>Baſil</hi> I do meane) in the nienth Summe of his moralls,<note place="margin">Cap. 22.</note> ſaith, <hi>If all that which is not of faith, be ſinne</hi> (as the Apoſtle ſaith) <hi>and faith commeth by hearing, and hearing by the word of God then all that which is out of the diuine, &amp; holy ſcripture, is ſinne.</hi> Againe in a
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:12501:34"/>
Sermon, which hee maketh of the confeſſion of faith, <hi>If God be faithfull in all his purpoſes, and his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandementes be ſure for euer, being done in trueth and right, it is manifeſtly to turne from the faith, and a ſinne of pride, to throwe any thing away of that which is written, or to bring in any thing, which is not written.</hi> Thus much in anſwere to that, which our Romiſh rufflers do bellowe for their church, the power, and glorie thereof; And to ſhewe what a chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an may and ought ſafely to thinke of the church, and how to giue humble credit to the holy ſcriptures, and to giue to them their due authoritie.</p>
            <p>To this Oration made, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Colloquie</hi> had at <hi>Poyſſi,</hi> by that ſingular inſtrument, and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant of God <hi>Theodore Beza,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Papiſtes and their capitayne the Cardinall did not reply. For I thinke they had not the hartes to withſtand the trueth.
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:12501:35"/>
Yea they were ſo far from denying of it, that euen then, and there, their chiefe doctor <hi>Deſpenſe</hi> was, in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation thereof, content to ſaye, that hee did allowe that in generall, which was ſayde in this Oration of the church; and ſaide that hee had alwayes taken this for a wicked blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemie that ſome doe ſay, that The church is aboue the holy ſcriptures. But touching that, which was in this oration ſaide of the ordinarie ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Paſtors, hee was not yet ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſatisfied. He added that he did not take the paſtors of the Churches re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by the Goſpell to be lawfull miniſters, becauſe they had not the handes laide on them by the Biſhops. To this the doctor was aunſwered then,<note place="margin">Impoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of handes.</note> and thus; That there are markes of the lawfull calling of Paſtors; of which ſome are ſubſtantiall, and may not bee omitted; others may. Subſtantiall things not to bee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:12501:35"/>
are theſe; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt that the perſon admitted into the miniſterie bee ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to doe that office, wich is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned the miniſter of Chriſt in his church by the worde of God; which is, to preach truely the doctrin of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, and ſincerely to adminiſter y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſacramentes. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Agayne, that before his admiſſion he bee tryed, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined, howe fitt, and able hee is to doe this worke of the Lorde; and ſo he muſt by tryall be founde able in doctrine, and of a godly conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of life. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly that then hee be choſen to the office, by forme, and order of a lawefull election. But as touching impoſition of hands, it doth concerne but an externe forme, and ſerueth as it were but to put him in poſſeſſion, and vſe of the holy mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie; it doth not make him a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter; it is not of any ſuch force. <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> writing againſt the <hi>Luciferians,</hi> ſaith expreſſely, that the impoſition
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:12501:36"/>
of handes is not of neceſſitie preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed by the law; but it is a certaine ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour done to the prieſthoode. <hi>Eliah,</hi> and <hi>Samuel</hi> did both of them ſacrifice; and yet did not any of the ordinary prieſtes lay their handes on them. It may be further ſaide in anſwere, that if the romiſh maiſters now wil needs haue vs to receiue impoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of hands of them, or elſe they will not take vs to be lawfull miniſters, they muſte ſhew firſt that them ſelues are right, and lawfull miniſters of the goſpell of Ieſus. But that they cannot do. For touching their inſtitution, it is as ſtrange, and vnknowne to the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, as was the inſtitution of the prieſtes of <hi>Ieroboams</hi> calues ſtrange to lawe of God. For the Romiſh prieſts are inſtituted to haue authoritie <hi>to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer ſacrifice to God, and to ſay maſſe for the quick and the dead,</hi> as the Popes <hi>Pontifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> beareth record, and that in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of the lord (ſay they.) But the Popiſh
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:12501:36"/>
               <hi>Pontificall</hi> doeth herein greatly abuſe the name of the Lord. For the Lord God doeth not in the whole newe Teſtament ordeyne any ſuch kinde of ſacrifizing, or maſſing Prieſtes. And therefore the order of the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh prieſthood is as farre wide from the goſpell, as the calues of <hi>Ieroboam</hi> were from the lawe of God; and his prieſtes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lords prieſtes. Now in the execution of that office, which the Prieſtes in poperie pretende to haue, and to exerciſe, they doe like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe depart from the trueth. For they preach not the goſpell of Ieſus, but the deuiſes of men, contrarie to the doctrin of Ieſus. They do not admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter his holy ſacraments according to Chriſtes holy ordinance, but they do, foraſmuch as in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lieth, corrupt the ſacrament of baptiſme, &amp; the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thereof with their mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold, &amp; very groſſe ceremonies, thogh they leaue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of it vncha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged.
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:12501:37"/>
And they do take vpon them boldly to change, (as they ſay) both the ſubſtance of the other ſacrament; that is, of the bodie and bloode of Chriſt our Sauiour, and alſo the ende why it was ordeined; ſo that they doe not leaue vs of this holy ſacrament nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the doctrine in truth, nor y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of it, nor the ende, and vſe of it; as their deuiſes of the <hi>Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation,</hi> and ſacrifice of their maſſe do declare to all the worlde. Therefore the impoſition of the handes of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſhe Biſhoppes, beeing them ſelues ſtraungers to the goſpel, is vtterly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meete for them which are called to do the office of a miniſter of the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell. The olde true Prieſtes in the old Teſtament did not receiue impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of handes of any of the Prieſtes of <hi>Baal,</hi> or other Idolatrous prieſts. In the Eccleſiaſticall hiſtorie we do read of diuerſe godly fathers, and Paſtors, which woulde not receiue the impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:12501:37"/>
of handes of ſuch Biſhops as were heretikes. Neither truely ought the miniſters of the goſpell of Ieſus ſeeke to haue anye impoſition of handes of the popiſh prieſtes, or ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtardly Biſhops of Poperie, which are both Idolaters &amp; heretikes. Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this is not neceſſarie, neither were it comely. The miniſters and prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of the goſpell, they haue this good teſtimonie of their vocation. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, that they are called to preache the goſpell. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Then they haue ben ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined, &amp; tryed by thoſe, to whome the gouernement of the church is in thoſe matters committed. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, they are found meete for the vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and choſen to it. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Laſt of all, they are with ſolemne prayers admitted into the charge, and put in poſſeſsion of it; admitted, and accepted of the people. And this is of force ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent in trueth to proue the lawfulnes of their miniſterie, and ſufficiencie
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:12501:38"/>
of their calling. They need not oyle; no not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> conſecrated oyle, to which the Popiſh Biſhops doe attribute a maruellous vertue of conſecrating, and bleſsing. They neede not the blind bleſsing of any of the popiſh Biſhops; no more than they neede y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhearing, or ſhauing of their crownes, which toyes are the cogniſance of the ſworne ſoldiers of thoſe Biſhops which are the tryed peticaptaines of the Pope, the very prieſtes of <hi>Baal.</hi> Thoſe two horned beaſts do, among them of Rome, take on them one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the authoritie to lay on handes. Let them, if they wil, lay their hands on them in their popiſh prieſthood, which are like to them ſelues. On the miniſters of the goſpell, which haue nothing like to them in the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie of it, their handes are not to be layde.<note place="margin">Eſr. 4.2.</note> The reſtorers of <hi>Hieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> woulde not receiue the offered helpe of their neighbours, which
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:12501:38"/>
were mockers of their labours, and enemies to it. And ſhall wee then ſeeke your helpe, (ô you Papiſtes) or receiue your profered ſeruice to helpe vs forwarde in the worke of the Lorde committed to vs? No, no; ye are deadly enimies to the worke of the Lorde, and mockers of it. Therefore wee will not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit your handes to be layde on vs. If the Lorde of his mercy ſhall turne the hearts of any of the popiſh cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, and giue them grace to loath their order, and giue them a deſire to ſerue the Lorde Ieſus in the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie of his holy goſpell, and the church ſhall neede their ſeruice, let them come to vs to be tryed, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined of vs, and if they be founde meete, and the church haue neede of their ſeruice; they ſhall receiue of vs impoſition of handes.</p>
            <p>And where is that commiſsion giuen, whereby the popiſh Biſhops
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:12501:39"/>
alone do claime the authoritie to lay on their vnholy hands vpon the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſters of the goſpell? Truely, neither can wee finde it in the olde, nor in the newe Teſtament. And in his time <hi>Hierome</hi> did write to one <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uagrius,</hi> that the impoſition of hands by the Biſhop, as it was then vſed, was no ordinance of God, but onely a cuſtome. Let the tryall of a true miniſter then not reſt vpon cuſtom, or encroching vnder the couer of ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies; but let it reſt in the true ſubſtance of the miniſterie; which is in doctrine, and doing the office of an Euangelicall miniſter. The Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh rulers wil driue vs to proue our calling either by doctrine, or by mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle. Touching doctrine, the word of God approueth our miniſterie ſufficiently: We neede not to auow the working of miracles; For the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuers of the doctrine, which is preached by vs, do proue it for vs, in
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:12501:39"/>
that their vnfeigned conuerſion to God is miraculouſly wrought in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the power of his worde. This doeth ſhewe forth the lawfull, faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and fruitefull labour, to which we are called by the grace, and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of God. This is no ſtrange mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, if you conſider that, which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> that they by his preaching of the Goſpell, and his miniſterie in it, beeing called, and conuerted from idolatrie, to knowe and worſhip the lord God in trueth; from wickedneſſe to holineſſe of life, were (as he ſayth) <hi>the ſeales of his Apoſtleſhip in the Lord.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 9.</note> And by what authoritie can they of Rome, who are moſt of all men out of rule, lay this lawe vppon the Lord our God, that he cannot, or ſhall not extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily call at his pleaſure any meet man to the miniſterie of his holye worde, vnleſſe the ſame man do firſt paſſe vnder their baſtardly handes, &amp;
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:12501:40"/>
be approued of them, who are moſte meete to be reproued of all other; as both by their inſtitution, and execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it is proued. Therefore amend your ſelues (ô you hollowe hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites of Rome) and leaue your vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt carping of vs. Turne your wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let, and pull out the beame, that ſtic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in your owne eyes. The Lorde amende you, if it be his holy will, &amp; proſper the preaching of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly goſpel, by the miniſterie of the miniſters of the goſpell for euer. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:12501:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
